<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title></title><!-- Title for your edition.  Not the title of the original document -->
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt><!-- This is where you put information about the digital edition you're creating -->
                <publisher></publisher>
                <pubPlace></pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <p></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc><!-- This is where you put information about the source you're digitizing -->
                <bibl>
                    <title></title>
                    <author></author>
                    <publisher></publisher>
                    <date></date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc><!-- This is an optional element where you should put information about the encoding choices you made -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p></p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl></tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc><!-- This is an optional element where you can put non-bibliographic (usually contextual) information about the source you're digitizing -->
            <creation><date></date></creation>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc><!-- This is where you keep track of the changes you make to your file -->
            <change who="" when=""></change>
            <change who="" when=""></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb facs="230" xml:id=""/> <!--am I missing something here?-->
            <div1> <!-- fix pg numbers-->
                <lg> 
                    <head type="main-authorial" rend="underline">The Bewitching Queen of Aeaea</head> <!-- This is the group of tags you would use to encode poetry.<l> -->
                    <l>We reached the Aeolian island next, the home of Aeolus,</l>
                    <l>Hippotas' son, beloved by the gods </l>
                    <l>who never die-a great floating island it was, and round it all</l>
                    <l>huge ramparts rise of indestructible bronze</l>
                    <l>and sheer rock cliffs shoot up from sea to sky.</l>
                    <l>The king had sired twelve children within his halls</l>
                    <l>six daughters and six sons in the lusty prime of youth,</l>
                    <l>so he gave his daughters as wives to his six sons.</l>
                    <l>Seated beside their dear father and doting mother</l>
                    <l>with delicacies aplenty spread before them,</l>
                    <l>they feast on forever ... All day long,</l>
                    <l>the halls breathe the savor of roasted meats</l>
                    <l>and echo round to the low moan of blowing pipes,</l>
                    <l>and all night long, each one by his faithful mate,</l>
                    <l>they sleep under soft-piled rugs on corded bedsteads.</l>
                        <pb facs="231" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>To this city of theirs we came, their splendid palace,</l>
                    <l>and Aeolus hosted me one entire month, he pressed me for news</l>
                    <l>of Troy and the Argive ships and how we sailed for home,</l>
                    <l>and I told him the whole long story, first to last.</l>
                    <l>And then, when I begged him to send me on my way,</l>
                    <l>he denied me nothing, he went about my passage.</l>
                    <l>He gave me a sack, the skin of a full-grown ox,</l>
                    <l>binding inside the winds that howl from every quarter,</l>
                    <l>for Zeus had made that king the master of all the winds,</l>
                    <l>with power to calm them down or rouse them as he pleased.</l>
                    <l>Aeolus stowed the sack inside my holds, lashed so fast</l>
                    <l>with a burnished silver cord</l>
                    <l>not even a slight puff could slip past that knot.</l>
                    <l>Yet he set the West Wind free to blow us on our way</l>
                    <l>and waft our squadron home. But his plan was bound to fail,</l>
                    <l>yes, our own reckless folly swept us on to ruin...</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Nine whole days we sailed, nine nights, nonstop.</l>
                    <l>On the tenth our own land hove into sight at last-</l>
                    <l>we were so close we could see men tending fires.</l>
                    <l>But now an enticing sleep came on me, bone-weary</l>
                    <l>from working the vessel's sheet myself, no letup,</l>
                    <l>never trusting the ropes to any other mate,</l>
                    <l>the faster to journey back to native land.</l>
                    <l>But the crews began to mutter among themselves,</l>
                    <l>sure I was hauling troves of gold and silver home,</l>
                    <l>the gifts of open-hearted Aeolus, Hippotas' son.</l>
                    <l>'The old story!' One man glanced at another, grumbling.</l>
                    <l>'Look at our captain's luck-so loved by the world,</l>
                    <l>so prized at every landfall, every port of call.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>'Heaps of lovely plunder he hauls home from Troy,</l>
                    <l>while we who went through slogging just as hard,</l>
                    <l>we go home empty-handed.'</l>
                        <lb>
                        </lb>
                    <l>'Now this Aeolus loads him</l>
                    <l>down with treasure. Favoritism, friend to friend!'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>'Hurry, let's see what loot is in that sack,</l>
                        <pb facs="232" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>how much gold and silver. Break it open-now!'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>A fatal plan, but it won my shipmates over.</l>
                    <l>They loosed the sack and all the winds burst out</l>
                    <l>and a sudden squall struck and swept us back to sea,</l>
                    <l>wailing, in tears, far from our own native land.</l>
                    <l>And I woke up with a start, my spirit churning-</l>
                    <l>should I leap over the side and drown at once</l>
                    <l>or grin and bear it, stay among the living?</l>
                    <l>I bore it all, held firm,</l>
                    <l>hiding my face, clinging tight to the decks</l>
                    <l>while heavy squalls blasted our squadron back</l>
                    <l>again to Aeolus' island, shipmates groaning hard.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>We disembarked on the coast, drew water there</l>
                    <l>and crewmen snatched a meal by the swift ships.</l>
                    <l>Once we'd had our fill of food and drink</l>
                    <l>I took a shipmate along with me, a herald too,</l>
                    <l>and approached King Aeolus' famous halls and here</l>
                    <l>we found him feasting beside his wife and many children.</l>
                    <l>Reaching the doorposts at the threshold, down we sat</l>
                    <l>but our hosts, amazed to see us, only shouted questions:</l>
                    <l>'Back again, Odysseus-why? Some blustering god attacked you?</l>
                    <l>Surely we launched you well, we sped you on your way</l>
                    <l>to your own land and house, or any place you pleased.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So they taunted, and I replied in deep despair,</l>
                    <l>'A mutinous crew undid me-that and a cruel sleep.</l>
                    <l>Set it to rights, my friends. You have the power!'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So I pleaded-gentle, humble appeals-</l>
                    <l>but our hosts turned silent, hushed... </l>
                    <l>and the father broke forth with an ultimatum:</l>
                    <l>'Away from my island-fast-most cursed man alive!</l>
                    <l>It's a crime to host a man or speed him on his way</l>
                    <l>when the blessed deathless gods despise him so.</l>
                    <l>Crawling back like this-</l>
                        <pb facs="233" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>it proves the immortals hate you! Out-get out!'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Groan as I did, his curses drove me from his halls </l>
                    <l>and from there we pulled away with heavy hearts,</l>
                    <l>with the crews' spirit broken under the oars' labor,</l>
                    <l>thanks to our own folly ... no favoring wind in sight.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Six whole days we rowed, six nights, nonstop.</l>
                    <l>On the seventh day we raised the Laestrygonian land,</l>
                    <l>Telepylus heights where the craggy fort of Lamus rises.</l>
                    <l>Where shepherd calls to shepherd as one drives in his flocks</l>
                    <l>and the other drives his out and he calls back in answer,  </l>
                    <l>where a man who never sleeps could rake in double wages,</l>
                    <l>one for herding cattle, one for pasturing fleecy sheep,</l>
                    <l>the nightfall and the sunrise march so close together.</l>
                    <l>We entered a fine harbor there, all walled around</l>
                    <l>by a great unbroken sweep of sky-scraping cliff</l>
                    <l>and two steep headlands, fronting each other, close</l>
                    <l>around the mouth so the passage in is cramped.</l>
                    <l>Here the rest of my rolling squadron steered,</l>
                    <l>right into the gaping cove and moored tightly,</l>
                    <l>prow by prow. Never a swell there, big or small;</l>
                    <l>a milk-white calm spreads all around the place.</l>
                    <l>But I alone anchored my black ship outside,</l>
                    <l>well clear of the harbor's jaws</l>
                    <l>I tied her fast to a cliffside with a cable.</l>
                    <l>I scaled its rock face to a lookout on its crest</l>
                    <l>but glimpsed no trace of the work of man or beast from there;</l>
                    <l>all I spied was a plume of smoke, drifting off the land.</l>
                    <l>So I sent some crew ahead to learn who lived there-</l>
                    <l>men like us perhaps, who live on bread?</l>
                    <l>Two good mates I chose and a third to run the news.</l>
                    <l>They disembarked and set out on a beaten trail</l>
                    <l>the wagons used for hauling timber down to town</l>
                    <l>from the mountain heights above ...</l>
                    <l>and before the walls they met a girl, drawing water,</l>
                    <l>Antiphates' strapping daughter-king of the Laestrygonians.  </l>
                        <pb facs="234" xml:id=""/>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>She'd come down to a clear running spring, Artacia,</l>
                    <l>where the local people came to fill their pails.</l>
                    <l>My shipmates clustered round her, asking questions:</l> 
                    <l>who was king of the realm? who ruled the natives here?</l> 
                    <l>She waved at once to her father's high-roofed halls.</l> 
                    <l>They entered the sumptuous palace, found his wife inside-</l>
                    <l>a woman huge as a mountain crag who filled them all with horror.</l> 
                    <l>Straightaway she summoned royal Antiphates from assembly,</l>
                    <l>her husband, who prepared my crew a barbarous welcome.</l> 
                    <l>Snatching one of my men, he tore him up for dinner-</l>
                    <l>the other two sprang free and reached the ships.</l> 
                    <l>But the king let loose a howling through the town</l>
                    <l>that brought tremendous Laestrygonians swarming up</l>
                    <l>from every side-hundreds, not like men, like Giants!</l>
                    <l>Down from the cliffs they flung great rocks a man could hardly hoist</l> 
                    <l>and a ghastly shattering din rose up from all the ships-</l>
                    <l>men in their death-cries, hulls smashed to splinters-</l>
                    <l>They speared the crews like fish</l> 
                    <l>and whisked them home to make their grisly meal.</l> 
                    <l>But while they killed them off in the harbor depths</l>
                    <l>I pulled the sword from beside my hip and hacked away</l>
                    <l>at the ropes that moored my blue-prowed ship of war</l> 
                    <l>and shouted rapid orders at my shipmates:</l> 
                    <l>'Put your backs in the oars-now row or die!'</l> 
                    <l>In terror of death they ripped the swells-all as one-</l>
                    <l>and what a joy as we darted out toward open sea,</l> 
                    <l>clear of those beetling cliffs ... my ship alone.</l> 
                    <l>But the rest went down en masse. Our squadron sank.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>From there we sailed on, glad to escape our death</l> <!--indent-->
                    <l>yet sick at heart for the dear companions we had lost.</l> 
                    <l>We reached the Aeaean island next, the home of Circe</l> 
                    <l>the nymph with lovely braids, an awesome power too</l> 
                    <l>who can speak with human voice,</l> 
                    <l>the true sister of murderous-minded Aeetes.</l>
                    <l>Both were bred by the Sun who lights our lives;</l> 
                    <l>their mother was Perse, a child the Ocean bore.</l>
                    <l>We brought our ship to port without a sound</l>
                <pb facs="235" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>as a god eased her into a harbor safe and snug,</l> 
                    <l>and for two days and two nights we lay by there,</l> 
                    <l>eating our hearts out, bent with pain and bone-tired.</l>
                    <l>When Dawn with her lovely locks brought on the third day,</l> 
                    <l>at last I took my spear and my sharp sword again,</l> 
                    <l>rushed up from the ship to find a lookout point,</l>
                    <l>hoping to glimpse some sign of human labor,</l> 
                    <l>catch some human voices ... </l>
                    <l>I scaled a commanding crag and, scanning hard,</l> 
                    <l>I could just make out some smoke from Circe's halls,</l> 
                    <l>drifting up from the broad terrain through brush and woods.</l> 
                    <l>Mulling it over, I thought I'd scout the ground-</l>
                    <l>that fire aglow in the smoke, I saw it, true, </l>
                    <l>but soon enough this seemed the better plan: </l>
                    <l>I'd go back to shore and the swift ship first,</l>
                    <l>feed the men, then send them out for scouting. </l><!--italics-->
                    <l>I was well on my way down, nearing our ship </l>
                    <l>when a god took pity on me, wandering all alone; </l>
                    <l>he sent me a big stag with high branching antlers,</l>
                    <l>right across my path-the sun's heat forced him down </l>
                    <l>from his forest range to drink at a river's banks-</l>
                    <l>just bounding out of the timber when I hit him </l>
                    <l>square in the backbone, halfway down the spine </l>
                    <l>and my bronze spear went punching clean through-</l>
                    <l>he dropped in the dust, groaning, gasping out his breath. </l>
                    <l>Treading on him, I wrenched my bronze spear from the wound,</l>
                    <l>left it there on the ground, and snapping off some twigs </l>
                    <l>and creepers, twisted a rope about a fathom long, </l>
                    <l>I braided it tight, hand over hand, then lashed </l>
                    <l>the four hocks of that magnificent beast. </l>
                    <l>Loaded round my neck I lugged him toward the ship, </l>
                    <l>trudging, propped on my spear-no way to sling him </l>
                    <l>over a shoulder, steadying him with one free arm-</l>
                    <l>the kill was so immense! </l>
                    <l>I flung him down by the hull and roused the men,</l>
                    <l>going up to them all with a word to lift their spirits:</l>
                    <l>'Listen to me, my comrades, brothers in hardship-</l>
                    <l>we won't go down to the House of Death, not yet, </l>
                <pb facs="236" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>not till our day arrives. Up with you, look, </l>
                    <l>there's still some meat and drink in our good ship.</l>
                    <l>Put our minds on food-why die of hunger here?</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>My hardy urging brought them round at once. </l>
                    <l>Heads came up from cloaks and there by the barren sea</l>
                    <l>they gazed at the stag, their eyes wide-my noble trophy.</l>
                    <l>But once they'd looked their fill and warmed their hearts,</l>
                    <l>they washed their hands a prepared a splendid meal.</l>
                    <l>Now all day long till the sun went down we sat </l>
                    <l>and feasted on sides of meat and seasoned wine. </l>
                    <l>Then when the sun had set and night came on</l>
                    <l>we lay down and slept at the water's shelving edge.</l>
                    <l>When young Dawn with her rose-red fingers shone once more</l>
                    <l>I called a muster quickly, informing all the crew,</l>
                    <l>'Listen to me, my comrades, brothers in hardship,</l>
                    <l>We can't tell east from west, the dawn from the dusk,</l>
                    <l>Nor where the sun that lights our lives goes under earth</l>
                    <l>Nor where it rises. We must think of a plan at once,</l>
                    <l>Some cunning stroke. I doubt there's one still left.</l>
                    <l>I scaled a commanding crag and from that height </l>
                    <l>surveyed an entire island</l>
                    <l>ringed like a crown by endless wastes of sea.</l>
                    <l>But the land itself lies low, and I did see smoke</l>
                    <l>Drifting up from its heart through thick brush and woods.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>My message broke their spirit as they recalled </l>
                    <l>The gruesome work of the Laestrygonian king Antiphates</l>
                    <l>And the heart cannibal Cyclops thirsting for our blood.</l>
                    <l>They burst into cries, wailing, streaming live tears</l>
                    <l>That gained us nothing-what good can come of grief?</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>And so, numbering off my band of men-at-arms </l>
                    <l>Into two platoons, I assigned them each a leader:</l>
                    <l>I took one and lord Eurylochus the other.</l>
                    <l>We quickly shook lots in a bronze helmet-</l>
                    <l>The lot of brave Eurylochus leapt out first.</l>
                    <l>So he moved off with his two and twenty comrades,</l>
                <pb facs="237" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>Weeping, leaving us behind in tears as well... </l>
                    <l>Deep in the wooded glens they came on Circe's palace </l>
                    <l>built of dressed stone on a cleared rise of land.</l>
                    <l>Mountain wolves and lions were roaming around the grounds-</l>
                    <l>She'd bewitched them herself, she gave them magic drugs.</l>
                    <l>But they wouldn't attack my men; they just came pawing</l>
                    <l>Up around them, fawning, swishing their long tails-</l>
                    <l>Eager as hounds that fawn around their master,</l>
                    <l>Coming home from a feast,</l>
                    <l>Who always brings back scraps to calm them down.</l>
                    <l>So they came nuzzling round my men-lions, wolves </l>
                    <l>with big powerful claws-and the men cringed in fear </l>
                    <l>at the sight of those strange, ferocious beasts...but still</l>
                    <l>They paused at her doors, the nymph with lovely braids,</l>
                    <l>Circe-and deep inside they heard her singing, lifting</l>
                    <l>Her spellbinding voice as she glided back and forth</l>
                    <l>At her great immortal loom, her enchanting web</l>
                    <l>A shimmering glory only goddesses can weave.</l>
                    <l>Polites, captain of armies, took command,</l>
                    <l>The closest, most devoted man I had: 'Friends,</l>
                    <l>There's someone inside, plying a great loom,</l>
                    <l>And how she sings-enthralling!</l>
                    <l>The whole house is echoing to her song.</l>
                    <l>Goddess or woman-let's call out to her now!'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So he urged and the men called out and hailed her. </l>
                    <l>She opened her gleaming doors at once and stepped forth,</l>
                    <l>Inviting them all in, and they went, all innocence.</l>
                    <l>Only Eurylochus stayed behind-he sensed a trap...</l>
                    <l>She ushered them in to sit on high-backed chairs,</l>
                    <l>Then she mixed them a potion-cheese, barley,</l>
                    <l>And pale honey mulled in Pramnian wine-</l>
                    <l>But into the brew she stirred her wicked drugs</l>
                    <l>To wipe from their memories any thought of home.</l>
                    <l>Once they'd drained the bowls she filled, suddenly</l>
                    <l>She struck her wand, drove them into her pigsties,</l>
                    <l>All of them bristling into swine-with grunts,</l>
                    <l>Snouts-even their bodies, yes, and only</l>
                <pb facs="238" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>The men's minds stayed steadfast as before.</l>
                    <l>So off they went to their pens, sobbing, squealing</l>
                    <l>As Circe flung them acorns, cornel nuts and mast,</l>
                    <l>Common fodder for hogs that root and roll in mud.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Back Eurylochus ran to our swift black ship </l>
                    <l>to tell the disaster our poor friends had faced.</l>
                    <l>But try as he might, he couldn't get a word out. </l>
                    <l>Numbing sorrow had stunned the man to silence-</l>
                    <l>tears welled in his eyes, his heart possessed by grief. </l>
                    <l>We assailed him with questions-all at our wits' end-</l>
                    <l>till at last he could recount the fate our friend had met: </l>
                    <l>'Off we went through the brush, captain, as you commanded. </l>
                    <l>Deep in the wooded glens we came on Circe's palace </l>
                    <l>built of dressed stone on a cleared rise of land. </l>
                    <l>Someone inside was plying a great loom,</l>
                    <l>and how she sang-in a high clear voice! </l>
                    <l>Goddess or woman-we called out and hailed her ... </l>
                    <l>She opened her gleaming doors at once and stepped forth, </l>
                    <l>inviting us all in, and in we went, all innocence. </l>
                    <l>But I stayed behind-I sensed a trap. Suddenly</l>
                    <l>all vanished-blotted out-not one face showed again, </l>
                    <l>though I sat there keeping watch a good long time.' </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>At that report I slung the hefty bronze blade</l>
                    <l>of my silver-studded sword around my shoulder, </l>
                    <l>slung my bow on too and told our comrade, </l>
                    <l>'Lead me back by the same way that you came.' </l>
                    <l>But he flung both arms around my knees and pleaded, </l>
                    <l>begging me with his tears and winging words: </l>
                    <l>'Don't force me back there, captain, king-</l>
                    <l>leave me here on the spot. </l>
                    <l>You will never return yourself, I swear,</l>
                    <l>you'll never bring back a single man alive.</l>
                    <l>Quick, cut and run with the rest of us here-</l>
                    <l>we can still escape the fatal day!' </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>But I shot back, 'Eurylochus, stay right here, </l>
                <pb facs="239" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>eating, drinking, safe by the black ship.  </l>
                    <l>I must be off. Necessity drives me on.' </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Leaving the ship and shore, I headed  inland, </l>
                    <l>clambering up through  hushed,  entrancing  glades until, </l>
                    <l>as I was nearing the halls of Circe skilled in spells, </l>
                    <l>approaching  her palace-Hermes  god of the golden wand  </l>
                    <l>crossed my path, and he looked for all the world  </l>
                    <l>like a young  man  sporting his first beard, </l>
                    <l>just in the prime and warm  pride of youth, </l>
                    <l>and grasped me by the hand and asked me kindly,  </l>
                    <l>'Where  are you going now, my unlucky  friend- </l>
                    <l>trekking  over the hills alone in unfamiliar country?</l>
                    <l>And your men  are all in there,  in Circe's palace,  </l>
                    <l>cooped like swine, hock by jowl in the sties.  </l>
                    <l>Have you come to set them free?  </l>
                    <l>Well, I warn  you, you won't  get home yourself,  </l>
                    <l>you'll stay right there, trapped  with all the rest.  </l>
                    <l>But wait, I can save you, free you from that great danger.  </l>
                    <l>Look, here is a potent drug. Take it to Circe's halls- </l>
                    <l>its power alone will shield you from the fatal day. </l>
                    <l>Let me tell you of all the witch's subtle craft ...</l>   
                    <l>She'll mix you a potion, lace the brew with drugs</l> 
                    <l>but she'll be powerless to bewitch you, even so- </l>
                    <l>this magic herb I give will fight her spells.</l>  
                    <l>Now here's  your plan of action, step by step. </l> 
                    <l>The moment  Circe strikes with her long thin wand,</l> 
                    <l>you draw your sharp sword sheathed at your hip</l>
                    <l>and rush her fast as if to run her through! </l>
                    <l>She'll cower in fear and coax you to her bed- </l>
                    <l>but don't refuse the goddess' bed, not then,  not if</l>  
                    <l>she's to release your friends and treat you well yourself.</l> 
                    <l>But have her swear the binding oath of the blessed gods</l>
                    <l>she'll never  plot some new  intrigue  to harm you, </l>
                    <l>once you lie there naked- </l>
                    <l>never  unman  you, strip away your courage!'</l>  
                    <l>With that</l> <!--indent-->
                    <l>the giant-killer handed  over the magic herb,</l>
                <pb facs="240" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>pulling it from the earth,</l>
                    <l>Hermes showed me all its name and nature. </l>
                    <l>Its root is black and its flower white as milk</l>
                    <l>and the gods call it moly. Dangerous for a mortal man</l>
                    <l>to pluck from the soil but not for deathless gods.</l>
                    <l>All lies within their power.</l> 
                    <l>Now Hermes went his way</l> <!--indent-->
                    <l>to the steep heights of Olympus, over the island's woods</l>
                    <l>while I, just approaching the halls of Circe, </l>
                    <l>my heart a heaving storm at every step, </l>
                    <l>paused at her doors, the nymph with lovely braids-</l>
                    <l>I stood and shouted to her there. She heard my voice,</l>
                    <l>she opened the gleaming doors at once and stepped forth, </l>
                    <l>inviting me in, and in I went, all anguish now ... </l>
                    <l>She led me in to sit on a silver-studded chair, </l>
                    <l>ornately carved, with a stool to rest my feet. </l>
                    <l>In a golden bowl she mixed a potion for me to drink, </l>
                    <l>stirring her poison in, her heart aswirl with evil.</l> 
                    <l>And then she passed it on, I drank it down </l>
                    <l>but it never worked its spell-</l>
                    <l>she struck with her wand and 'Now,' she cried, </l>
                    <l>'off to your sty, you swine, and wallow with your friends!' </l>
                    <l>But I, I drew my sharp sword sheathed at my hip</l>
                    <l>and rushed her fast as if to run her through-</l>
                    <l>She screamed, slid under my blade, hugged my knees </l>
                    <l>with a flood of warm tears and a burst of winging words: </l>
                    <l>'Who are you? where are you from? your city? your parents?</l> 
                    <l>I'm wonderstruck-you drank my drugs, you're not bewitched!</l> 
                    <l>Never has any other man withstood my potion, never,</l>
                    <l>once it's past his lips and he has drunk it down.</l>
                    <l>You have a mind in you no magic can enchant! </l>
                    <l>You must be Odysseus, man of twists and turns-</l>
                    <l>Hermes the giant-killer, god of the golden wand, </l>
                    <l>he always said you'd come, </l>
                    <l>homeward bound from Troy in your swift black ship. </l>
                    <l>Come, sheathe your sword, let's go to bed together, </l>
                    <l>mount my bed and mix in the magic work of love-</l>
                    <l>we'll breed deep trust between us.'</l>
                </lg>
                <pb facs="241" xml:id=""/>
                <lg>
                    <l>So she enticed </l><!--indent-->
                    <l>but I fought back, still wary. 'Circe, Circe,</l>
                    <l>how dare you tell me to treat you with any warmth?</l>
                    <l>You who turned my men to swine in your own house and now</l>
                    <l>You hold me here as well-teeming with treachery</l>
                    <l>You lure me to your room to mount your bed,</l>
                    <l>So once I lie there naked</l>
                    <l>You'll unman me, strip away my courage!</l>
                    <l>Mount your bed? Not for all the world. Not</l>
                    <l>Until you consent to swear, goddess, a binding oath</l>
                    <l>You'll never plot some new intrigue to harm me!'</l>
                    <l>Straightaway </l><!--indent-->
                    <l>She began to swear the oath that I required-never,</l>
                    <l>She'd never do me harm-and when she'd finished,</l>
                    <l>Then, at last, I mounted Circe's gorgeous bed...</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>At the same time her handmaids bustles through the halls,</l>
                    <l>Four in all who perform the goddess' household tasks:</l>
                    <l>Nymphs, daughters born of the springs and groves</l>
                    <l>And the sacred rivers running down to open sea.</l>
                    <l>One draped the chairs with fine crimson covers</l>
                    <l>Over the seats she'd spread with linen cloths below.</l>
                    <l>A second drew up silver tables before the chairs</l>
                    <l>And laid out golden trays to hold the bread.</l>
                    <l>A third mulled heady, heart-warming wine</l>
                    <l>In a silver bowl and set out golden cups.</l>
                    <l>A fourth brought water and lit a blazing fire</l>
                    <l>Beneath a massive cauldron. The water heated soon,</l>
                    <l>And once it reached the boil in the glowing bronze</l>
                    <l>She eased me into a tub and bathed me from the cauldron,</l>
                    <l>Mixing the hot and cold to suit my taste, showering</l>
                    <l>Head and shoulders down until she'd washed away</l>
                    <l>The spirit-numbing exhaustion from my body.</l>
                    <l>The bathing finished, rubbing me sleek with oil,</l>
                    <l>Throwing warm fleece and a shirt around my shoulders,</l>
                    <l>She led me in to sit on a silver-studded chair,</l>
                    <l>Ornately carved, with a stool to rest my feet.</l>
                    <l>A maid brought water soon in a graceful golden pitcher</l>
                <pb facs="242" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>and over a silver basin tipped it out</l>
                    <l>so I might rinse my hands, </l>
                    <l>then pulled a gleaming table to my side. </l>
                    <l>A staid housekeeper brought on bread to serve me, </l>
                    <l>appetizers aplenty too, lavish with her bounty. </l>
                    <l>She pressed me to eat. I had no taste for food. </l>
                    <l>I just sat there, mind wandering, far away ... </l>
                    <l>lost in grim forebodings. </l>
                    <l>As soon as Circe saw me, </l><!--indent-->
                    <l>huddled, not touching my food, immersed in sorrow, </l>
                    <l>she sidled near with a coaxing, winged word: </l>
                    <l>'Odysseus, why just sit there, struck dumb, </l>
                    <l>eating your heart out, not touching food or drink? </l>
                    <l>Suspect me of still more treachery? Nothing to fear.</l> 
                    <l>Haven't I just sworn my solemn, binding oath?' </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So she asked, but I protested, 'Circe-</l>
                    <l>how could any man in his right mind endure </l>
                    <l>the taste of food and drink before he'd freed </l>
                    <l>his comrades-in-arms and looked them in the eyes? </l>
                    <l>If you, you really want me to eat and drink, </l>
                    <l>set them free, all my beloved comrades-</l>
                    <l>let me feast my eyes.' </l>
                    <l>So I demanded.</l> <!--indent-->
                    <l>Circe strode on through the halls and out, </l>
                    <l>her wand held high in hand and, flinging open the pens, </l>
                    <l>drove forth my men, who looked like full-grown swine. </l>
                    <l>Facing her, there they stood as she went along the ranks, </l>
                    <l>anointing them one by one with some new magic oil-</l>
                    <l>and look, the bristles grown by the first wicked drug </l>
                    <l>that Circe gave them slipped away from their limbs</l>
                    <l>and they turned men again: younger than ever,</l>
                    <l>taller by far, more handsome to the eye, and yes, </l>
                    <l>they knew me at once and each man grasped my hands </l>
                    <l>and a painful longing for tears overcame us all,</l> 
                    <l>a terrible sobbing echoed through the house ... </l>
                    <l>The goddess herself was moved and, standing by me, </l>
                    <l>warmly urged me on-</l>
                    <l>a lustrous goddess now: </l>
                <pb facs="243" xml:id=""/>
                    <l>'Royal son of Laertes, Odysseus, tried and true,</l>  
                    <l>go at once to your ship at the water's  edge, </l> 
                    <l>haul her straight up on the shore first  </l>
                    <l>and stow your cargo and running  gear in caves,  </l>
                    <l>then back you come and bring your trusty crew.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Her urging won  my stubborn  spirit over. </l> 
                    <l>Down I went to the swift ship at the water's  edge, </l>
                    <l>and there on the decks I found my loyal crew  </l>
                    <l>consumed with grief and weeping  live warm  tears. </l> 
                    <l>But now, as calves in stalls when cows come home,  </l>
                    <l>droves of them herded back from field to farmyard  </l>
                    <l>once they've grazed their fill-as all their young calves  </l>
                    <l>come frisking out to meet them, bucking  out of their pens, </l>
                    <l>lowing nonstop, jostling, rushing  round  their mothers- </l>
                    <l>so my shipmates there at the sight of my return </l> 
                    <l>came pressing round  me now,  streaming  tears,</l>  
                    <l>so deeply moved in their hearts they felt as if </l> 
                    <l>they'd  made it back to their  own land, their city, </l>
                    <l>Ithaca's  rocky soil where  they  were bred and reared.</l>
                    <l>And through  their  tears their words went  winging home: </l> 
                    <l>'You're back again, my king! How thrilled  we are.</l> 
                    <l>as if we'd reached  our country,  Ithaca,  at last! </l> 
                    <l>But come, tell us about the fate our comrades  met.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Still I replied with  a timely word of comfort:</l>  
                    <l>'Let's haul  our  ship straight up on the shore first </l> 
                    <l>and stow our cargo and running  gear in caves.</l>  
                    <l>Then hurry, all of you,  come along with  me </l> 
                    <l>to see our friends in the magic halls of Circe,</l>   
                    <l>eating and drinking-the  feast flows on forever.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So I said and they jumped  to do my bidding.</l>  
                    <l>Only Eurylochus  tried to hold my shipmates back,</l>  
                    <l>his mutinous outburst aimed  at one and all:</l>  
                    <l>'Poor fools, where are we running now?</l> 
                    <l>Why are we tempting fate?-</l>
                    <l>why stumble blindly down to Circe's halls? </l>
                <pb facs="244" xml:id=""/> 
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>She'll turn us all into pigs or wolves or lions</l>
                    <l>made to guard that palace of hers-by force, I tell you-</l>
                    <l>just as the Cyclops trapped our comrades in his lair</l>
                    <l>with hotheaded Odysseus right beside them all-</l>
                    <l>thanks to this man's rashness they died too!'</l> <!-- italics on they -->
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So he declared and I had half a mind </l>
                    <l>to draw the sharp sword from beside my hip</l> 
                    <l>slice his head off, tumbling down in the dust,</l>
                    <l>close kin that he was. But comrades checked me, </l>
                    <l>each man trying to calm me, left and right: </l>
                    <l>'Captain, we'll leave him here if you command,</l> 
                    <l>just where he is, to sit and guard the ship. </l>
                    <l>Lead us on to the magic halls of Circe.' </l>
                    <l>With that</l><!--indent-->
                    <l>up from the ship and shore they headed inland.</l> 
                    <l>Nor did Eurylochus malinger by the hull; </l>
                    <l>he straggled behind the rest, </l>
                    <l>dreading the sharp blast of my rebuke. </l>
                    <l>All the while</l> <!--indent-->
                    <l>Circe had bathed my other comrades in her palace, </l>
                    <l>caring and kindly, rubbed them sleek with oil </l>
                    <l>and decked them out in fleecy cloaks and shirts. </l> 
                    <l>We found them all together, feasting in her halls.</l> 
                    <l>Once we had recognized each other, gazing face-to-face, </l>
                    <l>we all broke down and wept-and the house resounded now</l>
                    <l>Circe the lustrous one came toward me, pleading, </l>
                    <l>'Royal son of Laertes, Odysseus, man of action,</l>
                    <l>no more tears now, calm these tides of sorrow. </l>
                    <l>Well I know what pains you bore on the swarming sea, </l>
                    <l>what punishment you endured from hostile men on land. </l>
                    <l>But come now, eat your food and drink your wine </l>
                    <l>till the same courage fills your chests, now as then,</l>
                    <l>when you first set sail from native land, from rocky Ithaca! </l>
                    <l>Now you are burnt-out husks, your spirits haggard, sere, </l>
                    <l>always brooding over your wanderings long and hard, </l>
                    <l>your hearts never lifting with any joy-</l>
                    <l>you've suffered far too much.'</l>
                <pb facs="245" xml:id=""/> 
                    <l>So she enticed </l><!--indent-->
                    <l>and won our battle-hardened spirits over.</l>
                    <l>And there we sat at ease,</l>
                    <l>Day in, day out, till a year had run its course,</l>
                    <l>Feasting on sides of meat and drafts of heady wine...</l>
                    <l>But then, when the year was through and the seasons wheeled by </l>
                    <l>And the months waned and the long days came round again,</l>
                    <l>My loyal comrades took me aside and prodded,</l>
                    <l>'Captain, this is madness!</l>
                    <l>High time you thought of your own home at last,</l>
                    <l>If it really is your fate to make it back alive</l>
                    <l>And reach your well-built house and native land.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Their urging brought my stubborn spirit round.</l>
                    <l>So all that day till the sun went down we sat</l>
                    <l>And feasted on sides of meat and heady wine.</l>
                    <l>Then when the sun had set and night came on</l>
                    <l>The men lay down to sleep in the shadowed halls</l>
                    <l>But I went up to that luxurious bed of Circe's,</l>
                    <l>Hugged her by the knees</l>
                    <l>And the goddess heard my winging supplication:</l>
                    <l>'Circe, now make good a promise you gave me once-</l>
                    <l>It's time to help me home. My heart longs to be home,</l>
                    <l>My comrades' hearts as well. They wear me down,</l>
                    <l>Pleading with me whenever you're away.'</l>
                    <l>So I pressed </l><!--indent-->
                    <l>And the lustrous goddess answered me in turn:</l>
                    <l>'Royal son of Laertes, Odysseus, old campaigner,</l>
                    <l>Stay on no more in my house against your will.</l>
                    <l>But first another journey calls. You must travel down</l>
                    <l>To the house of death and the awesome one, Persephone,</l>
                    <l>There to consult the ghost of Tiresias, seer of Thebes,</l>
                    <l>The great blind prophet whose mind remains unshaken.</l>
                    <l>Even in death-persephone has given him wisdom,</l>
                    <l>Everlasting vision to him and him alone...</l>
                    <l>The rest of the dead are empty, flitting shades.'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So she said and crushed the heart inside me.</l>
                <pb facs="246" xml:id=""/> 
                    <l>I knelt in her bed and wept. I'd no desire </l>
                    <l>to go on living and see the rising light of day. </l>
                    <l>But once I'd had my fill of tears and writhing there, </l>
                    <l>at last I found the words to venture, 'Circe, Circe,</l> 
                    <l>who can pilot us on that journey? Who has ever </l>
                    <l>reached the House of Death in a black ship?'</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>The lustrous goddess answered, never pausing,</l> 
                    <l>'Royal son of Laertes, Odysseus, born for exploits,</l> 
                    <l>let no lack of a pilot at the helm concern you, no,</l> 
                    <l>just step your mast and spread your white sail wide-</l>
                    <l>sit back and the North Wind will speed you on your way.</l> 
                    <l>But once your vessel has cut across the Ocean River </l>
                    <l>you will raise a desolate coast and Persephone's Grove,</l> 
                    <l>her tall black poplars, willows whose fruit dies young. </l>
                    <l>Beach your vessel hard by the Ocean's churning shore </l>
                    <l>and make your own way down to the moldering House of Death.</l>
                    <l>And there into Acheron, the Flood of Grief, two rivers flow,</l> 
                    <l>the torrent River of Fire, the wailing River of Tears </l>
                    <l>that branches off from Styx, the Stream of Hate,</l> 
                    <l>and a stark crag looms </l>
                    <l>where the two rivers thunder down and meet. </l>
                    <l>Once there, go forward, hero. Do as I say now. </l>
                    <l>Dig a trench of about a forearm's depth and length </l>
                    <l>and around it pour libations out to all the dead-</l>
                    <l>first with milk and honey, and then with mellow wine,</l> 
                    <l>then water third and last, and sprinkle glistening barley </l>
                    <l>over it all, and vow again and again to all the dead, </l>
                    <l>to the drifting, listless spirits of their ghosts,</l> 
                    <l>that once you return to Ithaca you will slaughter </l>
                    <l>a barren heifer in your halls, the best you have, </l>
                    <l>and load a pyre with treasures-and to Tiresias,</l> 
                    <l>alone, apart, you will offer a sleek black ram,</l> 
                    <l>the pride of all your herds. And once your prayers</l> 
                    <l>have invoked the nations of the dead in their dim glory, </l>
                    <l>slaughter a ram and black ewe, turning both their heads </l>
                    <l>toward Erebus, but turn your head away, looking toward </l>
                    <l>the Ocean River. Suddenly then the countless shades</l> 
                <pb facs="247" xml:id=""/> 
                    <l>of the dead and gone will surge around you there.</l> 
                    <l>But order your men at once to flay the sheep </l>
                    <l>that lie before you, killed by your ruthless blade,</l> 
                    <l>and burn them both, and then say prayers to the gods,</l> 
                    <l>to the almighty god of death and dread Persephone.</l> 
                    <l>But you-draw your sharp sword from beside your hip,</l> 
                    <l>sit down on alert there, and never let the ghosts </l>
                    <l>of the shambling, shiftless dead come near that blood </l>
                    <l>till you have questioned Tiresias yourself. Soon, soon </l>
                    <l>the great seer will appear before you, captain of armies: </l>
                    <l>he will tell you the way to go, the stages of your voyage,</l> 
                    <l>how you can cross the swarming sea and reach home, at last.'</l> 
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>And with those words Dawn rose on her golden throne </l>
                    <l>and Circe dressed me quickly in sea-cloak and shirt </l>
                    <l>while the queen slipped on a loose, glistening robe, </l>
                    <l>filmy, a joy to the eye, and round her waist </l>
                    <l>she ran a brocaded golden belt </l>
                    <l>and over her head a scarf to shield her brow. </l>
                    <l>And I strode on through the halls to stir my men,</l> 
                    <l>hovering over each with a winning word: 'Up now!</l> 
                    <l>No more lazing away in sleep, we must set sail-</l>
                    <l>Queen Circe has shown the way.'</l> 
                    <l>I brought them round,</l> <!--indent-->
                    <l>my hardy friends-in-arms, but not even from there</l> 
                    <l>could I get them safely off without a loss ... </l>
                    <l>There was a man, Elpenor, the youngest in our ranks,</l>
                    <l>none too brave in battle, none too sound in mind. </l>
                    <l>He'd strayed from his mates in Circe's magic halls </l>
                    <l>and keen for the cool night air,</l>
                    <l>sodden with wine he'd bedded down on her roofs. </l>
                    <l>But roused by the shouts and tread of marching men, </l>
                    <l>he leapt up with a start at dawn but still so dazed</l>
                    <l>he forgot to climb back down again by the long ladder-</l>
                    <l>headfirst from the roof he plunged, his neck snapped</l>
                    <l>from the backbone, his soul flew down to Death. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Once on our way, I gave the men their orders:</l> 
                <pb facs="248" xml:id=""/> 
                    <l>'You think we are headed home, our own dear land? </l>
                    <l>Well, Circe sets us a rather different course ...</l> 
                    <l>down to the House of Death and the awesome one, Persephone,</l> 
                    <l>there to consult the ghost of Tiresias, seer of Thebes.'</l> 
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>So I said, and it broke my shipmates' hearts.</l> 
                    <l>They sank down on the ground, moaning, tore their hair.</l>
                    <l>But it gained us nothing-what good can come of grief?</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Back to the swift ship at the water's edge we went, </l>
                    <l>our spirits deep in anguish, faces wet with tears.</l> 
                    <l>But Circe got to the dark hull before us, </l>
                    <l>tethered a ram and black ewe close by-</l>
                    <l>slipping past unseen. Who can glimpse a god </l>
                    <l>who wants to be invisible gliding here and there?" </l>
                </lg>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
